<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Joshua Stevens</title>
  <subtitle>Cartography and Visualization</subtitle>
  <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/</id>
  <link href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/"/>
  <link href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-08-08T01:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>HDRI Lighting for Shaded Relief Maps</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/cartography/hdri-lighting-for-shaded-relief-maps/"/>
    <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/cartography/hdri-lighting-for-shaded-relief-maps/</id>
    <published>2014-08-08T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-08T18:47:01-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Josh</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/shadedRelief_featured.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaded relief maps are among my favorite of all map types. Not only do they form the foundation for many other maps and derivative layers, they present a fascinating challenge: depicting an abstraction of terrain in a natural way while balancing accuracy with aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This push and pull between modeling a natural phenomenon (the illumination of Earth and the shadows cast by the sun) with artistic purposes has captivated cartographers for centuries. It&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that as technology advanced, so too did the modeling of the sun&amp;rsquo;s rays. With this in mind, I wondered how techniques in 3D ray tracing carry over to shaded relief mapping. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Shaded Relief&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In common GIS software, relief mapping is made relatively easy. Typically, the user inputs a Digital Elevation Model (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_elevation_model"&gt;DEM&lt;/a&gt;) and specifies some parameters for the sun - most often its altitude, azimuth, and ambient strength. The software then decides, based on a simulation of light cast with these properties, which features of the elevation model are lit and which are not. This process forms a gradient of shadows and highlights that reveal the structure of the terrain, based on the height of the terrain and how directly it faces the source of the light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a major drawback to this process in common GIS software: it only identifies which terrain features are lit directly by the sun, and how strongly each is lit. In the natural world, light does not terminate once it strikes an object - it reflects. The reflected ray, now slightly diminished in strength, might then strike another feature. Again, the ray is reflected, and this process continues until the angle of reflection sends the ray skyward or the light has been absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Ray Tracing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accurately modeling the bouncing of light across objects, and how it reflects, refracts, and depletes is known as &lt;a href="https://www.cs.unc.edu/~rademach/xroads-RT/RTarticle.html"&gt;ray tracing&lt;/a&gt; in the 3D modeling world. In 3D modeling and rendering software, one has much more control over light sources than is provided by most GIS software. In addition to simulating light rays more accurately, most 3D modeling software can depict various textures to further refine how light behaves. For instance, you could specify your terrain to be shiny, diffuse, or even to emit its own light. As a result, 3D applications provide much more control over the simulation of light and shadows, and are therefore an attractive alternative for shaded relief mapping. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Huffman has a great &lt;a href="http://somethingaboutmaps.wordpress.com/2014/01/01/blender-tutorial/"&gt;tutorial series&lt;/a&gt; showing how this can be done in Blender, an open source 3D modeling application. The results are superb and I highly recommend this technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray tracing is typically done with one (or more) kinds of light sources. In Blender, there are &lt;a href="http://wiki.blender.org/index.php/Doc:2.6/Manual/Lighting/Lamps"&gt;5 types of light sources&lt;/a&gt; - or &amp;ldquo;lamps.&amp;rdquo; A &lt;strong&gt;point&lt;/strong&gt; lamp emits light spherically in all directions. A &lt;strong&gt;spot&lt;/strong&gt; lamp directionally aims light, similar to a flashlight. An &lt;strong&gt;area&lt;/strong&gt; lamp emits light from a planar surface. A &lt;strong&gt;hemi&lt;/strong&gt; lamp emits light in a 180° arc, and a &lt;strong&gt;sun&lt;/strong&gt; lamp mimics (you guessed it) the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these light sources have various parameters that can be adjusted, such as size, distance, intensity, direction, and color. They also have vary different behaviors and produce different results. For instance, illuminating a DEM with a small point light will create sharp highlights nearest the source with an obvious dimming at greater distances:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/point_5size_1750int.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DEM ray traced using a small, low intensity point light. Yuck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can mitigate this effect slightly by increasing both the size and intensity of the point light. Increasing the size will more evenly light the area at all distances, though the light will become much weaker. To compensate, the intensity of the light also needs to be increased. Doing so produces the following result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/point_40size_12500.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DEM ray traced using a large, high intensity point light. Meh&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result above is a little better, but the shadows in the southeast still indicate their distance from the light. Let&amp;rsquo;s crank up the intensity some more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/point_40size_42000.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DEM ray traced using a large, very high intensity point light. Slightly better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall there is some improvement, but again, it is evident that the terrain nearest the light is being lit much more than distant features. We could theoretically keep increasing the distance of the point light, while ramping up its intensity, to provide fully uniform lighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or we could just use the sun lamp, which increasing the distance and intensity of the point lamp would only approximate. When using the sun lamp, we gain much more even lighting and a rather realistic depiction of shadows. Notice the increased range of shadows in the highlighted region:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/plainSun_detail.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the sun lamp produces a much better result, with clearer indications of reflected light from a completely uniform source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a ray traced sun produces a relief map that is incredibly well lit. It has smooth gradations between light and dark while persevering highlighted peaks and deep, dark shadows where necessary. With a few minor tweaks, I would be very happy with this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;High Dynamic Range Imagery&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I became a cartographer I used to dabble in Lightwave and other 3D applications. As a high school student, I&amp;rsquo;d create 3D meshes for others to buy and use in their own projects. One of the best ways to advertise the quality of a model was to render it in a stunningly well-lit environment. Since it would take a lot of time to model a forest, or a futuristic kitchen full of appliances, I stumbled across a shortcut: &lt;a href="http://www.unparent.com/photos_probes.html"&gt;HDRI probes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_dynamic_range_imaging"&gt;HDRI&lt;/a&gt;, or High Dynamic Range Imaging, is a method for capturing photos with a much greater range of luminosity than is typical of conventional photography. When combined with a file format (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RGBE_image_format"&gt;.hdr&lt;/a&gt;) that stores much more data per pixel, it becomes possible to retain an enormous amount of the light-emitting properties of an image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since HDR images are so luminous, 3D modelers often use them to light their scenes. This technique has three primary advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of lighting objects in a uniform color, as is done in GIS software and single-source 3D techniques, HDR images emit both &lt;a href="http://dativ.at/lightprobes/"&gt;light &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; color&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;HDR lighting greatly reduces rendering time. Since the equivalent in a fully modeled world would require numerous objects and multiple &amp;ldquo;bounces&amp;rdquo; of light, cutting out these steps saves a ton of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;With effective depth-of-field, HDR images can serve as the backdrop of a scene.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last item isn&amp;rsquo;t really important for relief mapping since we often depict terrain orthographically, so the area surrounding the terrain is out of view. But the first two are incredibly useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Using HDRI Lighting for Shaded Relief&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using HDR images as a light source first requires a &lt;em&gt;probe.&lt;/em&gt; These are HDR photos, often of spheres with a mirror surface, that can be projected onto other surfaces. By reprojecting the image back onto the inside of a hollow sphere, you can mimic the environment and ambient light sources of the original scene. The example below shows an HDR probe of Galileo&amp;rsquo;s Tomb, and a scene rendered using that probe. There are no other light sources in the scene; everything is lit with ambient light as if it sat in the same room in which the probe was taken:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/galileo_example.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An HDR probe of Galileo&amp;rsquo;s Tomb (left) and a mesh rendered using the probe as a light source. Images from &lt;a href="http://www.pauldebevec.com/Probes/"&gt;Paul Debevec&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would a shaded relief look like using this technique? To find out, I created a scene in which the DEM was lit by Galileo&amp;rsquo;s Tomb (a fitting example for a geographic study). When rendered using this HDR probe, the shaded relief looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/tomb_015int.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DEM rendered with an HDR probe of Galileo&amp;rsquo;s Tomb. The terrain itself has no color (muted gray). The tone comes entirely from the HDR lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, this relief map looks a lot like the version rendered with the standard sun, though it is cast in the dominant color of the probe. Somewhat surprisingly, it is being lit from the northwest. I did not expect this, as HDR lighting illuminates the scene from all directions, with the strength dependent upon the light sources in the original images. The northwest lighting here is merely a convenient coincidence. If it had not occurred, we could easily rotate the probe within Blender to achieve the desired effect (or throw in a weak sun lamp to compensate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When Things Go Awry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For another example, I rendered the DEM using a probe of a beach scene. This time the angle of lighting did not work in my favor out of the box. Initially the scene was completely lit from the top [A]. To add northwest highlights, I placed a sun lamp with a relatively flat angle of illumination in the scene [B]. Since the HDR probe can be reprojected and rotated, I also generated a version where the water was the dominant feature [C]. This cast everything in deep blue, which is interesting but not exactly what we want. Similarly, [D] is the result of orienting the probe with the sand overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/beach_quad.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DEM rendered with alterations of a beach scene as an HDR probe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the dominant hue of the probe and its orientation strongly influence the lighting of the relief map. To show just how strong this effect is, I created a relief map using an HDR probe of a rainbow spectrum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/rainbow_relief.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if the world really needed another rainbow map&amp;hellip; This one has a purpose, though :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the relief map above, the entire scene is cast in a magenta hue. This is because HDR probes wrap in 360 degrees and when using a structured image (e.g., ordered hues) the leftmost pixels get stretched the most to complete the projection, resulting in an image that is mostly that color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope I&amp;rsquo;ve shown, HDR lighting can work for shaded relief mapping. Whether the relief map turns out adequately is highly dependent on the source image for the probe. But all in all, it is an interesting process and one I look forward to exploring more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when it works well, as in my first Galileo example, the final product is still cast in the dominant hue of the probe. So why would you ever want this in shaded relief maps, which generally remain completely neutral?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have three reasons why you might want to (your mileage may vary):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every event occurs at some location. Similarly, every event also happens at a &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt;. The combination of both space and time is often missing from most maps; this is especially true for shaded relief maps. Although there is value (and convenience) in depicting relief while ignoring time, I find there is an attraction in representing relief that hints at the passage of time. With HDR, one could generate relief maps that accurately depict the half light of dawn or an aurora passing overhead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even the phenomenal results of using a ray traced sun lacks the realism of natural light. Atmospheric scattering, ambient reflections, and the azure tinting of the environment that happens at great distances is wholly absent. With little effort, HDR lighting could provide some of these.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because you can.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it was just fun to explore different lighting techniques. This project began as an attempt to scratch the itch of curiosity, and although there are mixed results, I think HDR lighting for shaded relief shows potential - particularly for item 2 above. As I get more time, I intend to investigate that a little further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, I hope this provokes some thought and generates ideas on how we can more realistically (and even artistically) represent relief in maps with 3D software.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Open Source Copyright Infringement: Are DMCA Takedowns on GitHub Increasing?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/open-source-copyright-infringement/"/>
    <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/open-source-copyright-infringement/</id>
    <published>2014-07-07T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2014-07-07T21:01:08-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Josh</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/octocatThumb.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While browsing &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/linux"&gt;/r/linux&lt;/a&gt; I saw this post: &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/linux/comments/29vvz5/rate_of_dmca_takedown_demands_is_increasing_on/"&gt;Rate of DMCA takedown demands is increasing on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds pretty scary, for a couple of reasons. On one hand, it could mean that companies are really dropping the hammer and coming after folks more often and &lt;a href="https://torrentfreak.com/google-further-highlights-wrongful-dmca-takedowns-130320/"&gt;potentially in error&lt;/a&gt;. On the other, it could mean the open source community is becoming more lax or lazy, using others&amp;#39; code without respecting licenses or copyright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But could there be a third alternative? Is the rate of DMCA takedowns &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; increasing in a meaningful way? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately GitHub is open about the DMCA notices they receive. Since January 27, 2011 GitHub has &lt;a href="https://github.com/github/dmca"&gt;posted each request received and each counter-notice issued&lt;/a&gt;. All 317 of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here they are by month.
&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/dmca_by_month.png" alt="Are DMCAs issued to GitHub on the rise?" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph above shows the number of DMCA takedown requests issued each month, according to GitHub&amp;rsquo;s own DMCA repo.  Another redditor made a similar &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/linux/comments/29vvz5/rate_of_dmca_takedown_demands_is_increasing_on/cip1hk0"&gt;graph&lt;/a&gt; (though I suspect from the R code posted that they didn&amp;rsquo;t filter out counter-notices).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to this data there is clearly an upward trend in DMCA takedowns, with a peak of 41 in May 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Who is Issuing the Takedowns?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most companies or individuals who issue DMCA requests to GitHub do so only once. Such requests account for 68% of all DMCAs received by GitHub. The remaining 32% of takedowns come from just 30 sources. According to the original theory that the requests are on the rise, looking at the number of takedowns per originating party could help us identify who is cracking down on copyright the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, it could reveal who developers like to infringe upon the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/dmca_by_party.png" alt="Who is issuing the most DMCA takedowns to GitHub?" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, &lt;a href="https://codility.com/"&gt;Codility&lt;/a&gt; leads the pack - and by quite a bit. I expected Sony, Amazon, or others in the music industry to be the frontrunners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of takedowns from Codility becomes less surprising in the context of what Codility is: a service designed to help corporate recruiters test candidates for development positions. By having developers solve programming challenges, companies can quickly identify who has the desired skills and who does not. That saves hiring managers a lot time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also gives shady candidates an incentive to share questions, code snippets, and solutions to these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick perusal through Codility&amp;rsquo;s DMCA requests shows that&amp;rsquo;s precisely the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&amp;hellip;but are DMCA Takedowns Really on the Rise?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to answer the question about what is driving DMCA takedowns on GitHub. Are companies being more aggressive about their copyrighted code? Or are developers being more fast and loose with licenses or outright stealing? One thing is clear: the total number of DMCA requests to GitHub are higher than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What do More Frequent DMCA Requests Really Mean?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as DMCA requests are going up, the total number of repositories being created on GitHub are also increasing. Thus looking at DMCA takedowns is meaningless without considering the increase in projects over the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its launch in 2008, GitHub has seen &lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/1724-10-million-repositories"&gt;tremendous growth&lt;/a&gt;. Starting with zero users and no repositories, GitHub now boasts over &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/features"&gt;14 million repositories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. That number represents more than a doubling in repositories over the previous year. In the words of &lt;a href="https://github.com/briandoll"&gt;Brian Doll&lt;/a&gt; at GitHub:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first million repositories were created in just under 4 years; 3 years, 8 months and 15 days to be exact. This last million took just 48 days. In fact, over 5.5M repositories — more than half of the repositories on the site — were created this year alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a lot of new projects. With so many projects being created, it stands to reason that more DMCA requests will follow. More code &lt;i class="fa fa-arrow-right"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; more potential for infringement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To truly reflect a more aggressive campaign against infringement - or developers playing fast and loose with copyright, the rate of DMCA takedowns would have to grow more quickly than the rate of projects being created. So let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the rate of DMCA requests per 1,000,000 repositories over the last four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/dmca_per_million.png" alt="Well then..." /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly a different picture emerges. And one that should be a bit more uplifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frequency of DMCA requests to GitHub may be on the rise, but so far it is not out-pacing the rate of new projects. In fact, the proportion of repositories being issued DMCA notices is at an all-time low. 2014 is not over yet and a lot could happen in the coming months. But it would take an unprecedented deluge of DMCAs to upset the current trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to encouraging readers to put away the pitchforks, I hope this also prompts a closer look at DMCA requests and the growth of GitHub. With the &lt;a href="https://developer.github.com/v3/"&gt;GitHub API&lt;/a&gt; it becomes possible to do tons of really interesting analyses of code (others already have done some &lt;a href="http://www.itworld.com/big-data/410137/python-developers-are-most-giving"&gt;fantastic work with it&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you decide to do with the API, just don&amp;rsquo;t violate copyright - especially not under the watchful eye of Codility. And don&amp;rsquo;t rely on raw counts without taking a look at the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Visual Guide to Painful Hymenopteran Stings</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/visual-guide-to-painful-insect-stings/"/>
    <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/visual-guide-to-painful-insect-stings/</id>
    <published>2014-06-27T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2014-07-02T23:31:30-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Josh</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/stingFeatured.png" alt="View the other images to see which hymenopteran is the king of sting!" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of us, insect stings are a thing to avoid. That&amp;rsquo;s not the case for entomologist Justin O. Schmidt. That&amp;rsquo;s because Dr. Schmidt has dedicated his life to studying venomous hymenopterans, the order of insects made up of ants, bees, and wasps. Through his research, he has been stung countless times. As a result, he developed the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schmidt_sting_pain_index"&gt;Schmidt Sting Pain Index&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon Schmidt&amp;rsquo;s work after seeing &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1_K7Tp97PsE"&gt;this video of warrior wasps&lt;/a&gt;. One of the noteworthy characteristics of warrior wasps is that when threatened, they rhythmically flap their wings against their bodies in perfect synchrony, producing a sound not unlike marching soldiers. The other characteristic these wasps are known for is a sting that &lt;strong&gt;hurts!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just how much does a sting from a warrior wasp hurt? According to the pain index developed by Schmidt, the warrior wasp tops in at a 4 - the highest level of pain in the scale. What&amp;rsquo;s more, the excruciating pain will last at least 60 minutes before subsiding even the slightest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warrior wasp is not the most painful sting recorded in Schmidt&amp;rsquo;s index, however. In fact, it pales in comparison to some other insect stings. To date, Schmidt has cataloged the painful stings of nearly 80 different hymenopteran species, from various ants to the giant Asian hornet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So which venomous insect is really the king of sting? I&amp;rsquo;ve turned Schmidt&amp;rsquo;s data into this visualization to help you decide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/insectStingsFull.png" alt="The Schmidt Sting Pain Index, visualized" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the data provided by Schmidt, I&amp;rsquo;ve added the common name of the insect, or the group to which it belongs, where possible. Due to Schmidt&amp;rsquo;s expertise and rigor, many of the species listed are not commonly known. For these, I was unable to track down any common identifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pain is subjective. It&amp;rsquo;s possible that one person might prefer a short-lived category 4 sting over a longer, weaker category 1 or 2 sting. According to these data however, &lt;strong&gt;the bullet ant&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Paraponera clavata&lt;/em&gt;) is the clear winner. The immediate category 4 pain from a bullet ant lasts for &lt;em&gt;5 hours!&lt;/em&gt; It then takes 24 hours to subside, with residual pain reported up to two weeks later. No wonder it is considered the most painful sting not just among hymenopterans, but all other insects!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a powerful sting has earned the bullet ant a place among the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maw%C3%A9_people"&gt;Satere-Mawe&lt;/a&gt;, a tribe in the Brazilian Amazon rain forest. During their coming-of-age initiation, young members of the Satere-Mawe wear mittens lined with bullet ants. For 10 minutes  initiates dance in the stinging mittens to prove their courage. They must do this not once, but &lt;em&gt;20 times before&lt;/em&gt; completing their ceremonial journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Pain and Place: The Bodily Geography of Schmidt&amp;rsquo;s Index&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the subjective nature of pain, location matters when it comes to insect stings [&lt;a href="#refs"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;]. Using honey bees as a baseline, Michael L. Smith &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3994616/"&gt;tested the variance of Schmidt&amp;rsquo;s Pain Index&lt;/a&gt; based on where the sting occurred. According to Smith&amp;rsquo;s research, the nostril was the worst place to be stung, followed by the upper lip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/stingByLocationFull.png" alt="Sting Pain by Location" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timing of the sting and number of subsequent stings were not significant factors in pain level. Smith hypothesizes the important role of location is due to naturally protected areas that are rarely stimulated (e.g. nostrils) and soft areas that enable greater penetration. Even in its most sensitive locations, Smith notes that the human body has defenses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stings to the nostril were especially violent, immediately inducing sneezing, tears and a copious flow of mucus. The sting did autotomize in the nostril (self-severed when the bee was pulled away). The copious mucus flow, however, may help prevent subsequent stings to the area during a natural attack. (p. 6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Stings That Kill&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, bee and wasp stings are responsible for the deaths of about &lt;a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Health/AllergiesNews/story?id=8148229"&gt;40 people each year&lt;/a&gt;. This makes bees more deadly than dogs, spiders, and snakes [&lt;a href="#refs"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;]. Even sharks, which are one of the most feared animals in the world, have &lt;a href="http://oceana.org/en/our-work/protect-marine-wildlife/sharks/learn-act/shark-attack-statistics"&gt;only killed 3 people in the US during the years 2006 - 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all of the deaths related to bee stings are the result of &lt;a href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000033.htm"&gt;anaphylaxis&lt;/a&gt;, which is a severe allergic reaction that can lead to difficulty in breathing, dizziness, unconsciousness, and ultimately death. Anaphylaxis is the result of compounds in the insects&amp;#39; venom that are not related to the amount of pain inflicted. As a result, the Schmidt Pain Index is not an indicator of how deadly an animal is to humans. Small bees (pain level 1-2) kill far more people than the bullet ant (level 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deadliness of smaller, less painful insects has more to do with their behavior and the likelihood of an encounter. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Africanized_bees"&gt;Africanized honey bees&lt;/a&gt; - the famed &amp;ldquo;killer bees&amp;rdquo; - are particularly deadly because of their aggressive swarming characteristics. They are easier to provoke, attack in large numbers, and are known to chase their targets for long distances. Just last year, a man in Texas was killed after a swarm of nearly &lt;a href="http://www.usnews.com/news/newsgram/articles/2013/06/03/40000-killer-bees-sting-texas-man-to-death"&gt;40,000 killer bees&lt;/a&gt; descended upon him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Different Dose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as location affects pain, the biochemistry of the species&amp;#39; venom influences its lethality. Each species has a slightly different arrangement of enzymes in their venom, making some more lethal than others. In addition, each species injects a different amount of their venom, per sting. For example, the Honey bee injects 0.05mg of venom per sting while the fire ant can inject up to 0.1mg [&lt;a href="#refs"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;]. Typically, insects sting other insects or smaller animals that attempt to prey on them, so their venom has not evolved for the purpose of killing humans. But with a high enough dose - delivered by the right number of stings, hymenopteran venom &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be lethal. Just how much does it take?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/lethalityOfStingsFull.png" alt="Lethality of hymenopteran stings" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These data show the amount of venom required for death to occur as a result of the venom alone. Secondary effects, such as anaphylaxis, are not included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be tricked by the Giant hornet&amp;rsquo;s heavy-handed dose, however. Even though it can kill with the fewest stings, the fact that it delivers far more venom than the others means that, relatively speaking, its venom is not the most potent. To be lethal to a 50kg human, the Giant hornet must inject a total of 229.6 mg of venom. In contrast, a honey bee needs to inject only 175 mg of its venom. The graph below shows how these venoms stack up in terms of potency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/potencyOfVenomFull.png" alt="Potency of hymenopteran venom" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its high potency venom and greater likelihood to be encountered, its easy to see why the honey bee kills far more people than the giant hornet or any other hymenopteran!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="update"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is responsible for the most deaths and has more potent venom than some similar species, even the honey bee has weak venom compared to the most potent of all hymenopterans. That honor goes to the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pogonomyrmex_maricopa"&gt;Maricopa harvester ant&lt;/a&gt;. This species of ant has a venom that is nearly 30x more potent than the honey bee, making its venom the most potent of all insects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/honeyBeevsMaricopa.png" alt="The most potent of all hymenopterans"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s one thing to have the most potent insect venom. Having the most potent venom in the animal kingdom is another. How does the Maricopa harvester ant compare to the world&amp;rsquo;s most toxic snake and the poison dart frog? I wondered that too. As it turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s not even close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/toxicTrioFull.png" alt="The toxic trio: Sorry, hymenopterans. The frog wins!" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poison dart frog is more potent than any snake, spider, or ant venom. It even leaves the infamous Irukandji  box jellyfish and venomous cone snails (not pictured) in the dust.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to note the difference between poison and venom. Both are toxins that are produced to either protect the animal in defensive situations, or to help capture prey. The key difference is that venom is &lt;em&gt;injectected&lt;/em&gt; while poison is &lt;em&gt;injested.&lt;/em&gt; In other words, if it bites you and you die: it&amp;rsquo;s venomous. If &lt;em&gt;you bite it&lt;/em&gt; and you die: it&amp;rsquo;s poisonous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for us the poison dart frog fits in the latter category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from their interestingness, these data shattered a few of my preconceptions about insect stings. Being in the outdoors often has given me my fair share of stings and encounters with various bees, wasps, and hornets. Among all of these, I avoided hornets the most (the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bald-faced_hornet"&gt;bald-faced hornet&lt;/a&gt; is common in every area I&amp;rsquo;ve lived). I&amp;rsquo;m willing to bet that many others also view hornets as nastier, more painful stingers than other wasps and bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But according to the data, that needn&amp;rsquo;t be so. These hornets are no more painful than the common yellowjackets and bumble bees that frequent backyards and gardens. In fact, the pain subsides more quickly and their venom is much weaker. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Why would we fear the insects we see less frequently (such as hornets) while remaining comfortable around those most common to us (like honey bees) - despite the latter being more painful stingers and even more deadly? Personally, I think the question reveals the answer. As in many situations, it seems that fear of the unknown outweighs reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I won&amp;rsquo;t be hunting for a pet hornet anytime soon, I&amp;rsquo;m glad I took a look at these data and hope some of the findings were as eye-opening to you as they were for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="refs"&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class="smaller"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Schmidt, J. O. (1990). Hymenopteran venoms: striving toward the ultimate defense against vertebrates. &lt;em&gt;Insect defenses: adaptive mechanisms and strategies of prey and predators.&lt;/em&gt; State University of New York Press, Albany, 387-419.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Health Statistics. Compressed Mortality File 1999-2010 on CDC WONDER Online Database, released January 2013. Data are compiled from Compressed Mortality File 1999-2010 Series 20 No. 2P, 2013. Accessed at http://wonder.cdc.gov/cmf-icd10.html on Jun 28, 2014 1:00:26 PM&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Freeman, T. M. (2004). Hypersensitivity to hymenoptera stings. &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt;, 351(19), 1978-1984.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Smith ML. (2014) Honey bee sting pain index by body location. PeerJ 2:e338 &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/peerj.338"&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/peerj.338&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] Schmidt, J. O. (1983). Hymenopteran envenomation. &lt;em&gt;Urban entomology, interdisciplinary perspectives&lt;/em&gt;, 187.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Moving from WordPress to Middleman</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/site/moving-from-wordpress-to-middleman/"/>
    <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/site/moving-from-wordpress-to-middleman/</id>
    <published>2014-06-18T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2014-06-27T19:21:55-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Josh</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/rubyMMsass.png" alt="Ruby, Sass, and Middleman are awesome together." /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a few evenings removing WordPress and rebuilding this site on top of &lt;a href="http://www.middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt;. The new site is still a work in progress and I have more features to add, but all of the previous content has been brought over. It should be safe to launch this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did I do it? Over the past two years I&amp;rsquo;ve become increasingly frustrated with WordPress. Despite serving compressed pages, caching data, and reducing unnecessary scripts, page load times seemed to increase with each new version. Some of my more popular pages were averaging 5 seconds to load. That&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when WordPress itself performed well, it required additional plugins just to have reasonable features (e.g., caching, contact forms, spam protection, SEO optimization, etc.). Each of these requires constant updates, and one can never be sure if updating one plugin is going to break other plugins, or worse, the entire site. Compatibility reports from other users are helpful, but are often incomplete. Logging in just to write a simple post became a chore: update this, double check that, fix this other thing that the previous update broke, and so on. Long story short, it got old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/wpUpdates.png" alt="WordPress plugins are a chore to upkeep" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A familiar sight to WordPress users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, this site (and most blogs in general) really don&amp;rsquo;t need to be dynamic. Once published, the page content rarely changes. Involving a database and PHP scripts to deliver static content only adds unnecessary overhead. Under heavy load (thanks, &lt;a href="http://newsfeed.time.com/2013/09/23/want-to-find-bigfoot-now-theres-a-map-for-that/"&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;!) I found WordPress achingly slow. During my largest traffic spike page performance suffered so much that my email exploded with inquiries about it (on the bright side, it did not go down). Nonetheless, WordPress was no longer a pest that lived only on my web server: its shortcomings were now invading my inbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to switch to something else was a long time coming. Now that I had a few evenings to spare, I was able to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I set up Ruby, installed and configured Middleman, and re-developed everything from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The benefits have been immediate:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middleman is a roll-your-own beast. This site now does exactly what I want it to, no more, no less. No plugins to fuss with or break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middleman uses the &lt;a href="http://sass-lang.com/"&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt; CSS preprocessor and &lt;a href="http://compass-style.org/"&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt; framework. If you&amp;rsquo;re not already using Sass + Compass, I highly recommend them. They make rapidly deploying CSS designs incredibly painless by adding variables, mixins, and functions while removing the need to worry about vendor-specific prefixes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since all of the ruby scripts, Middleman configs and templates, and page content is first generated on my local machine, my entire site can be versioned on github and served via &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com"&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to do this before, but have been a bit hesitant. My post on &lt;a href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/squatch-watch-92-years-of-bigfoot-sightings-in-us-and-canada/"&gt;mapping sasquatch sightings&lt;/a&gt; generated a ton of discussion that I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to lose. Fortunately I could import all the comments to &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that all done, the new site is up and chugging along. Stay tuned for more content, and if you notice anything wonky please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Some tips on Middleman + Github Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of using Middleman with Github Pages, there are two ways to make it really easy. The first is to use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/neo/middleman-gh-pages"&gt;middleman-gh-pages&lt;/a&gt; extension. This adds rake tasks to deploy your site upon build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second method is to simply setup your &lt;code&gt;config.rb&lt;/code&gt; file to use your Github Pages repo as the build destination by adding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Change build directory to Github Pages repo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:build_dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'../YOUR_GH_NAME.github.io'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the approach I use. It is much cleaner - no additional rake tasks, overrides, or issues to worry about. In addition, it uses completely separate repositories for the development and production versions of your site. This enables you to test things out, revert changes, and ensure everything is working in a test environment before pushing the changes live, &lt;em&gt;even after a build&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, if you plan to use a custom 404 page, ensure your &lt;code&gt;404.html&lt;/code&gt; file is left as-is during the build operation. In &lt;code&gt;config.rb&lt;/code&gt; add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Exlude 404.html from being placed in a directory&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;page&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"/404.html"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:directory_index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kp"&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! Just run &lt;code&gt;$ bundle exec middleman build&lt;/code&gt; and commit the changes if you&amp;rsquo;re happy with how things work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Update: Was developing a static site worth it?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question comes down to whether or not it was worth the effort to redevelop a new site. Despite already being happier with the more minimal and personal design, I wanted to compare page load times between the old and new sites. Here are the average page load times for one week before the switch, and one week after:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/siteSpeed.png" alt="WordPress is slower than mollasses in January" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proof is in the pudding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say a 1500% improvement speaks for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Many Birthplaces of Memorial Day</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/thoughts/contentious-claims-memorial-days-origins/"/>
    <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/thoughts/contentious-claims-memorial-days-origins/</id>
    <published>2014-05-27T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2014-06-20T16:57:39-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Josh</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was Memorial Day. Like many other Americans, my family and I spent this day of national remembrance at a local park. We made the short trip to historic Boalsburg. Those in the know will recognize that Memorial Day in Boalsburg, PA is no ordinary affair. It is a massive celebration. This was especially true this year, which marks the 150th Memorial Day celebrated in Boalsburg. Thousands of people from all over gathered to honor our veterans who gave the ultimate sacrifice. What started as a time to decorate graves with flowers has now grown into a large festival, with celebratory events found at every corner of the township.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a learning opportunity. Almost everyone knows about Pennsylvania’s vital role in the Civil War and the importance of Memorial Day in the region. As a Michigan native, what I didn’t know was that Boalsburg itself was the very birthplace of Memorial Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least it claims to be.  After doing some reading, it turns out nearly two dozen towns – both North and South – claim to be the source of Memorial Day. Some of these claims are more legitimate than others. Some areas, like Savannah, GA, cite actual newspaper articles with specific dates. Others, like Knoxville, TN, rely on reports written long after the original event. Some locations do not provide any source at all – just secondhand mentions that such a claim was made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve gathered up a list of the locations that do have verifiable sources for their claims. Due to the nature of historic evidence (which might include everything from journal entires to Presidential Proclamations), this list is surely incomplete. But even still, the large number of towns that believe this special day started on their doorstep is, to me, quite interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Sourced claims of Memorial Day’s birthplace&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;iframe width="780" height="420" frameborder="0" seamless="true," src="http://www.joshuastevens.net/memorialDay/index.html"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the data comes from the &lt;a href="http://www.civilwarcenter.olemiss.edu/"&gt;Center for Civil War Research&lt;/a&gt;. Other sources include the &lt;a href="http://www.va.gov/opa/speceven/memday/"&gt;US Department of Veterans’ Affairs&lt;/a&gt;. Where possible, I linked to the actual township’s claim (via local website or newspaper).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Memorial Day vs Decoration Day&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memorial Day wasn’t always known by that name. Its original name, Decoration Day, was given by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_A._Logan"&gt;General John Logan&lt;/a&gt; of Illinois.  Nearly all stories about the birth of either holiday are based on one or more individuals placing flowers upon soldiers’ graves. Despite its northern namesake, a North-South distinction appears in the maintenance of Decoration Day. In the North (and now nationally) the day is most often recognized as Memorial Day. But in the South, many locations still celebrate Decoration Day in some capacity (this is also true of some Northern states). Regardless of the name, both the North and the South claim to have started this tradition around the end of the Civil War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, many historians believe graves were being decorated &lt;em&gt;during&lt;/em&gt; the war. Nella Sweet’s hymn &lt;a href="http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/scriptorium/sheetmusic/b/b08/b0802/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kneel Where our Loves Are Sleeping&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from 1867 is addressed to “The Ladies of the South who are decorating the graves of the Confederate dead.” Given that the hymn was written barely two years after the end of the Civil War, it is likely that Sweet was referring to an already established tradition. If you go back even further, you find that others had been doing this for centuries – and not just in America: there is evidence &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_funerals_and_burial"&gt;the practice first began in the Roman Empire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Does it matter who started it?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, absolutely not. This is being presented as a fun look at disputed history and bold claims. The true origins of Memorial Day may be forever disputed. I’m interested only in the geography of that dispute. The reason for the day is more important than the place of its origins. Because of this, I particularly like the disclaimer provided by the Center for Civil War Research, which states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the issue for many has been to determine, as definitively as may be, the true origin of the tradition, we feel it is more important to observe the power of the impulse to commemorate manifest among so many. We present here, hopefully without prejudice or favor, a survey of some of the early instances of the commemorative impulse — along with select references — that much later became the national holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;History’s Heroes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just a story of dispute. The real story exists in highlighting those honored by this day, and those who made it their goal to remember them. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_military_casualties_of_war"&gt;More than 1.3 million Americans have died in wars&lt;/a&gt;, and the number of deceased veterans is higher still. But death is not the only theme of Memorial Day. While reading through the various sources and claims, a clear trend emerges: regardless of location, this national day of remembrance and recognition was largely started by women and minorities. In the case of Charleston, SC, former slaves were responsible for commemorating (and honorably reburying) fallen Union soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether as a means to remember lost loved ones or to pay respects to those who gave their lives to defend ours, Memorial Day has a special place in American history. More importantly, it was a day born out of honor and commemoration – and no town can claim ownership of that.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Map of GDELT Predictions in Afghanistan as You Should Have Seen It</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/gdelt-prediction-map-seen/"/>
    <id>http://www.joshuastevens.net/visualization/gdelt-prediction-map-seen/</id>
    <published>2013-10-21T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2014-07-02T22:01:28-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Josh</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last several weeks, I’ve been creating a visualization of past and predicted conflicts in Afghanistan. The data, which come from a statistical model developed by &lt;a href="http://jayyonamine.com/"&gt;Jay Yonamine&lt;/a&gt; with help from &lt;a href="http://johnbeieler.org/"&gt;John Beieler&lt;/a&gt;, show us what might happen based on a long history of what has happened.  The database behind this model is known as &lt;a href="http://gdelt.utdallas.edu/"&gt;GDELT&lt;/a&gt;, or the Global Database of Events, Language, and Tone. GDELT has received &lt;a href="http://ideas.foreignpolicy.com/posts/2013/04/10/what_can_we_learn_from_the_last_200_million_things_that_happened_in_the_world"&gt;a lot of attention&lt;/a&gt; lately and I’ve participated in two hackathons that have emerged around it. After Wired showed interest in publishing this story along with the visualization, I was thrilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What You Saw&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I heard that &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/dangerroom/2013/10/afghanwarmaps/"&gt;Wired had published the work&lt;/a&gt; this morning, I was excited to check it out and see how the visualization tied the story together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I saw my map. Well, it was sort of my map. It had my name on it… but it was not at all how I had originally designed it. Here is the map as it is currently published:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/wired_afg_map-300x300.jpg" alt="Wired's bastardization of my original map." /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s my quibble:&lt;/strong&gt; Not only was my work altered without acknowledging the changes from the original, the change resulted in a red-green color scheme – a classic map mishap that no professional cartographer would ever make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve &lt;a href="http://www.joshuastevens.net/design/your-favorite-traffic-map-is-lying-to-you/"&gt;written about red/green colorblindness&lt;/a&gt; in the past. &lt;a href="http://blog.visual.ly/subtleties-of-color-addendum/"&gt;Others have too&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, advice on not using red/green color schemes on maps and other visualizations are practically &lt;a href="http://vis4.net/blog/posts/goodbye-redgreen-scales/"&gt;all&lt;/a&gt;[1] &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2000/04/000428082212.htm"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt;[2] &lt;a href="http://www.gislounge.com/making-color-blind-friendly-maps/"&gt;the&lt;/a&gt;[3] &lt;a href="http://misguidedmaps.com/2010/05/03/maps-for-the-colorblind/"&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;[4]. It’s not a new problem either: red/green color blindness has been written about by scientists for at least &lt;a href="http://archive.org/details/colourblindness00edrigoog"&gt;120 years&lt;/a&gt;. We even have tools, such as &lt;a href="http://colorbrewer2.org/"&gt;ColorBrewer&lt;/a&gt;, to help designers avoid common pitfalls with their color choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By being in red and green, this map is impossible to interpret by anyone affected by red/green colorblindness (almost 10% of  males, about 5% of the total population). Instead, readers with red/green colorblindness will see something like the image below (&lt;a href="http://www.color-blindness.com/2006/11/16/protanopia-red-green-color-blindness/"&gt;simulated protanopia&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/wired_afg_map_cb-300x300.png" alt="Wired's map, to someone with red-green colorblindness." /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wired&amp;rsquo;s map as seen by someone with red/green colorblindness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What You Should Have Seen&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that I intended to show readers &lt;strong&gt;a lot more about the data&lt;/strong&gt; – temporal trends, the propensity of conflicts near district and country borders, and the role of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Enduring_Freedom"&gt;Operation Enduring Freedom&lt;/a&gt; in the high number of material conflicts over the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I wanted you to see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="fullImage"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/afgEventsSmall.png" "My original GDELT visualization sent to Wired." /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view shows much more about the material conflicts that have occurred in Afghanistan over the past 34 years. From more than a million geocoded conflicts (check out the activity at the border between Afghanistan and Pakistan) to temporal trends, readers instantly get a better sense of the situation and how the data have changed over time. As a professional cartographer, I also made sure &lt;strong&gt;it is red/green colorblind-safe&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="/images/afgEvents_cbSafe.png"&gt;preview&lt;/a&gt;). Naturally, I would have liked to see this version published for the article’s readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I really can’t change the article. But I can share the original, and I hope it provides the utility and clarity that was intended – for all readers, colorblind or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
